A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Officers, RG 3 FA1797
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Correspondence and Subject Files, 1931-2017; 1; 12.65 Cubic Feet 35 containers
  - Black, Creed, 1971-1999; 1.1; 2.37 Cubic Feet 6 containers
    - Boulder Daily Camera, 1997 September 25 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      Knight File Number - 1597
      Letter from Creed Black re: grants to Boulder, CO after the sale of the Boulder Daily Camera by Knight-Ridder.
    - Knight-Ridder, 1998 June 12 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      Knight File Number - 1598
      Correspondence re: the relationship between Knight Foundation and Knight-Ridder, including supporting documents from legal counsel (1974-1998) Holland & Knight and Baker & Hostetler.
    - Community Anti-Drug Coalitions of America (CADCA), 1995 February 9 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      Knight File Number - 1599
      Meeting materials (agenda, list of attendees, letter) from the funding meeting in Miami for the Community Anti-Drug Coalitions of America (CADCA), which was hosted by Knight Foundation.
    - Board of Trustees, 1995 June 27 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      Knight File Number - 1602
      Memo from Jim Spaniolo to Lee Hills re: composition of the board, 1995, including a list of past board members and their terms of office.
    - Grant Evaluation, 1996 August 21 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      Knight File Number - 1833
      C. Black memo to trustees (Gerald Austen and Jill Conway) concerning evaluation (where we are, what we need, recommendations), in preparation for board meeting. Also included is a summary document entitled "Evaluation", which includes a memo from Creed Black to the Planning & Program Committee re: background on the proposed evaluation process, the Hamilton memo, and background reading.
    - Foundation Asset Rankings, 1998 January 27 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      Knight File Number - 2644
      Memo from Tim Crowe re: comparisons of asset size among the larger foundations for the years 1989 and 1996. Includes background data.
    - Performing Arts Center, 1995 February 21-1998 June 3 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      Knight File Number - 2729
      Correspondence regarding the possibility of making a grant to fund the Performing Arts Center in Miami, and the question of self dealing. Includes the request for a ruling on the self-dealing issue to the IRS, and subsequent correspondence. The IRS ruled in the Foundation's favor, as reported in a 1998 newsletter.
    - National Community Development Initiative, 1995 January 7-March 1 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      Knight File Number - 4791
      Correspondence and workplans re: NCDI communications programs for Boston and Cleveland.
    - Presidential Replacement, 1987 January 1-1988 December 31 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 981
      Correspondence related to the selection of Creed Black as the Knight Foundation's president in 1987.
    - Relocation of the Foundation, 1979 January 1-1993 December 22 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 1555
      Correspondence re: the relocation of the Foundation, including a letter addressing the move upon Creed Black's acceptance of the Presidency of the Foundation; C.C. Gibson letter voicing his objection to the move; and Creed Black's memo to Jim Knight, Lee Hills and Alvah Chapman re: his thoughts on moving the Foundation Headquarters from Akron (includes pencil comments from a reader). Includes background information on the issue of relocating the Foundation, John S. Knight's and Barbara Knight Toomey's views on the subject.
    - Presidential Search Committee, 1996 April 3-November 4 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 1578
      Correspondence of the Presidential Search Committee regarding the search for a new president to succeed Creed Black. Includes meeting materials and correspondence with the executive search firm Heidrick & Struggles.
    - Ohio Donors Forum, 1987 November 9 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 1600
      Letter from C.C. Gibson re: Knight Foundation's role in the Ohio Donors Forum. Marked "Personal and Confidential."
    - "Warehouses of Wealth", 1993 April 18-1994 May 5 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 2651
      Included in the folder is a copy of a series of critical articles on non-profit businesses (including foundations); an analysis of the articles prepared by the Council on Foundations; a summary of the articles prepared by "Give Five", a national forum to encourage giving, volunteering and not-for-profit initiative; talking points to try to negate criticism; and "Myths About Private Foundations", an analysis by the Council on Foundations
  - Carter, Hodding, 1992-2005; 1.2; 1.52 Cubic Feet 4 letter document boxes
    Hodding Carter, President. Mr. Carter's papers include folders on Community Initiatives issues of geographic eligibility, as well as larger issues such as changing the Knight Foundation cities.
    - Articles for Trustees, 2001 February 21-2005 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 3716
      Articles of interest, with notes, sent to the Trustees by Carter.
    - Advisory Committee Correspondence, 2000 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 3715
      Correspondence re: invitations to serve and resignations from the various Knight Foundation advisory committees.
    - Aspen Institute, 1999 February 2-June 20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 3717
      Regarding participation in The Aspen Institute's Conferences on Journalism and Society.
    - Community Advisors, 1998 June 5-September 9 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 1711
      Correspondence on the issue of possible proposal cycle changes and geographic eligibility, 1998.
    - Comparative Board Report, 2005 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 3718
      Report, prepared by the Center for Effective Philanthropy, provides insights into Knight Board of Trustee concerns and compares their responses with other foundation boards
    - Council on Foreign Relations, 1997 December 17-2004 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 3719
      Correspondence re: council meetings, membership, and Carter's participation in seminars and task forces.
    - General Correspondence, 1998 January 5-December 29 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
      Knight File Number - 3720
      Correspondence, including many hand-written notes from Hodding, mostly from professional colleagues, concerning a wide variety of topics, including speaking engagements. 2 folders.
    - General Correspondence, 1999 January 11-December 7 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
      Knight File Number - 3721
    - General Correspondence, 2000 February 28-December 21 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 3722
      Correspondence, including many hand-written notes from Hodding, mostly from professional colleagues, concerning a wide variety of topics, including speaking engagements.
    - General Correspondence, 2002 January 20-October 23 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 3723
    - General Correspondence, 2003 January 7-December 30 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
      Knight File Number - 3724
      Correspondence, including many hand-written notes from Hodding, mostly from professional colleagues, concerning a wide variety of topics, including speaking engagements. 2 folders
    - General Correspondence, 2004 January 6-December 29 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
      Knight File Number - 3725
    - General Correspondence, 2005 January 3-March 25 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 3726
    - Journalism, 1999 January 20-2000 December 6 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 3727
      Correspondence, notes and emails relating to a variety of topics of concern to Hodding Carter, especially the Knight Chairs, journalism grantees, the journalism advisory committee, and speaking engagements.
    - Journalism, 2001 January 4-November 29 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 3728
    - Knight Foundation Cities Change, 1997 August 1-1998 June 22 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 1710
      Correspondence and reports on the issue of changing the Knight Foundation cities (geographic eligibility), in light of KRI's sales and acquisitions of newspapers.
    - Journalism, 2002 January 14-December 12 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 3729
    - Journalism, 2003 January 10-2004 November 19 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 3730
    - Knight Foundation 50th Anniversary Celebration, 1999 April 15-2001 June 23 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 3731
      Correspondence, notes and emails relating to Knight Foundation's celebration of its 50th Anniversary. Includes a memo re: proposed publications; invitations and thank you notes from participants.
    - Legal Issues, 1998 November 11-1999 May 13 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 3849
      Memos prepared by KF counsel, Rod Petrey for Hodding Carter concerning the legal and moral duties of trustees, officers and senior staff at KF. Included are recommendations for action which Carter and KF's trustees were asked to consider. Also included are two memos (one from Rod Petrey, one from Bud Meyer) on the restrictions pertaining to lobbying by private foundations.
    - Outsourcing Knight Foundation's Investment Portfolio, 2004 November 1-2005 January 27 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 3732
      EnnisKnupp proposal for assistance in evaluating alternatives for management of Knight Foundation's investments; Cambridge Associates and Crowe Capital Partners' proposals for handling KF's investment portfolio; and memos to staff and trustees re: decision to go with Cambridge Associates. Also included is a letter from Dr. Austen to KF staff announcing the decision.
    - Panel on the Nonprofit Sector: Interim Report, 2005 March 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 3733
      The report, which sets forth the Panel's initial recommendations for strengthening the accountability of charities and foundations, was presented to the Senate Finance Committee. The report was funded, in part, with a grant from Knight Foundation.
    - Smart Growth Forum, 2000 May 12 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 3734
      The Smart Growth Forum was sponsored by the Knight Foundation. The meeting book includes an agenda, bios of speakers, and resource materials. The objective of the meeting was "to investigate the investment merits of smart growth real estate development projects."
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Alvarez, Cesar, 2000 November 6 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 2760
      Letter to Cesar Alvarez welcoming him to the Board of Trustees.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Austen, Gerald, 1996 May 20-2000 February 10 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 3735
      Correspondence re: meeting and staff logistics, on his retirement as surgeon-in-chief at Mass. General Hospital, the IDEAS fund, and discussion on trustee term and age limits.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Baker, Bud, 2004 February 11 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 3736
      Letter from trustee Bud Baker to Hodding Carter re: his visit to Knight Foundation for orientation.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Bare, John, 2001 January 17-2004 May 24 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 3737
      Emails and memos from John Bare, Director of Evaluation, re: project status and a series of exit memos on key individuals, strategic planning, budget trends, and pressing problems. Also included is information on Improving the Practices of Philanthropy project.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Black. Creed, 1996 May 28-2004 February 18 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 3738
      Includes a memo re: compensation for advisory committee members; transiton planning; Lee Hills; and the Knight Commission.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Briggs, Robert, 2002 May 6-2004 September 3 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 3739
      Correspondence with trustee Rob Briggs re: his interview with the nominating committee; his orientation to the Board; and the Grants Review Committee.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Chapman, Alvah, 2000 May 1-2003 June 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 3740
      Copy of a letter from Senator Bob Graham of Florida and Chapman's reponse; and several letters re: trustee meetings.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Coleman, Mary Sue, 2004 August 12-24 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 3741
      Two letters referring to trustee Coleman's decision to resign from the Knight Commission.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Conway, Jill Ker, 1992 April 6-2004 December 10 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 3742
      Correspondence with vice-chair Ker Conway re: board meetings, the death of her husband, planning committee matters, and her retirement from the board.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Crane, Marjorie, 1994 January 12-2000 August 15 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 3743
      Correspondence with trustee Marjorie Crane re: orientation, board issues, and strategic planning.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Crowe, Tim, 1996 August 2-2005 February 25 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 3744
      Correspondence with chief investment officer Tim Crowe re: technology; his salary; department staffing issues; strategic planning; his retirement and outsourcing of the investment department work.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Grogan, Paul, 2000 July 5-2004 March 26 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 3745
      Correspondence with trustee Paul Grogan re:his interview, election and orientation to the Board of Trustees.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Harris, Jay, 2003 June 16-2004 March 30 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 3746
      Correspondence with trustee Rob Briggs re: Hodding's attendance at a conference organized by Harris and a letter of recommendation of Harris by Hodding.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Heffern, Gordon, 2000 August 3-2004 March 11 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 3747
      Correspondence with trustee Gordon Heffern re: his desire for KF to add a faith-based area to its giving; and his retirement from the Board.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Hills, Lee, 1998 July 17-2000 November 20 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 3748
      Correspondence with trustee Lee Hills re: the Lee Hills Chair at the University of Missouri; and board issues.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Johnson, Tom, 2004 March 20 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 3749
      Letter from Tom Johnson re: asking Hodding to meet with a family friend over an investment opportunity.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Lawrence, Belinda, 1998 April 13-2005 February 25 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 3750
      Correspondence with chief administrative officer Belinda Lawrrence re: workforce culture, board issues, board compensation, benefits planning, and personnel issues.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Maidenberg, Michael, 1997 June 3-2004 August 16 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 3751
      Correspondence with chief program officer Mike Maidenberg re: his retirement from Knight-Ridder and the terms of his employment with KF.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - McPhee, Penny, 2004 February 3-September 24 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 3752
      Correspondence with former chief program officer Penny McPhee re: her leaving KF, and several exit memos.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Meyer, Larry, 1998 February 6-2004 April 15 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Knight File Number - 3753
      Correspondence with vice president of communications Larry Meyer re: Hodding's election to presidency; unauthorized use of KF's logo; Council on Foundations; negative reporting on KF; issues re the Annual Report; and a communication strategic plan.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Neill, Rolfe, 1992 April 24-2004 August 17 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Knight File Number - 3754
      Correspondence with trustee Rolfe Neill re: community initiatives proposal; and board issues.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Newton, Eric, 2001 May 16-2003 August 20 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Knight File Number - 3755
      Correspondence with Journalism program officer, Eric Newton, re: his hiring at KF; requests for funding for journalism issues; and his visit to China.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Noland, Mariam, 2002 June 14-2004 May 9 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      Knight File Number - 3756
      Correspondence with trustee Mariam Noland re: her election and orientation to the Board of Trustees.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Olson, Beverly, 1999 October 25-2004 July 9 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      Knight File Number - 3757
      Correspondence with trustee Beverly Olson re: an emergency grant to the Red Cross and family property.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Ong, John, 1999 April 1-2002 February 15 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      Knight File Number - 3758
      Correspondence with trustee John Ong re: his accommodations during board meetings, board issues, and his resignation from the board due to his being appointed US Ambassador to Norway.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Prude, Suzette, 2003 March 5-April 1 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      Knight File Number - 3759
      Correspondence with community liaison, Suzette Prude (Harvey) re: Miami community issues.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Rogers, John, 1999 June 11-2002 May 21 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      Knight File Number - 3760
      Correspondence with trustee John Rogers re: his vetting, nomination and election to the Board.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Stanford, Henry, 1999 May 17-2004 June 24 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      Knight File Number - 3761
      Correspondence with retired trustee Henry Stanford re: obituary of his wife, Ruth; and celebrations of his 88th birthday.
    - Staff/Trustee Correspondence - Versaci, Lisa, 2002 February 5-2003 March 27 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      Knight File Number - 3762
      Correspondence with National Venture Fund director, Lisa Versaci, re: grant inquiries; and a planning grant for a Fellows Program at the University of Pennsylvania.
  - Catrow, David, 1978-1990; 1.3; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
    David Catrow, Treasurer, Assistant Secretary and Office Manager. Six folders contain a memo to employees explaining retirement accounts (not dated), surveys of investment pool returns (1987), and expenses for charitable purposes (1989). More of Mr. Catrow's correspondence can be found in the files of the Finance Committee.
    - 403b Accounts (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 776
      Memo from David Catrow to Knight Foundation employees explaining their 403b accounts.
    - Investment Pool Return Surveys, 1987 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 777
      Memo from David Catrow and copy of Investment Return Surveys for Cambridge Associates. Includes historical return information, 1978-1987.
    - Legal Issues: Expenses for Charitable Purposes, 1989 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 778
      Memo from David Catrow to the Trustees re: allowable expenses for charitable purposes.
    - Securities and Exchange Commission filing, 1990 January 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 1150
      Signed copy of Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) Schedule 13G for filing re: Knight Ridder common shares.
    - First National Bank of Ohio, Original KF Pension Trust Agreement, 1978 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 1151
      Original KF pension trust agreement with First National Bank of Ohio, executed in 1978.
    - First National Bank of Ohio Trust Department, correspondence re: KF pension trust, 1979 March 30-1988 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 1152
      Correspondence of Dave Catrow and C.C. Gibson with First National Bank of Ohio's Trust Department, regarding the KF pension trust, 1979-1988.
  - Clark, Charles, 1979-1985; 1.4; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
    Charles Clark, Assistant Treasurer 1966-1969, Treasurer 1969-1989. These five folders, dating 1979-1985, contain information regarding fiduciary liability insurance, the financial state of the Foundation following the death of John S. Knight in 1981 and his bequest to Knight Foundation.
    - Fiduciary Liability Insurance, 1979 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 779
      Memo to C.C. Gibson from Charles Clark explaining the concept of fiduciary liability insurance, and how it affects the Trustees.
    - Correspondence, 1982 October 27-December 28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 780
      Correspondence from Charles Clark regarding the settlement of the estate of John S. Knight, and employee benefits.
    - Correspondence, 1983 February 3-November 17 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 781
      Correspondence regarding the estate of John S. Knight, and Knight-Ridder stock.
    - Correspondence, 1984 April 20-December 14 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 782
      Correspondence regarding excess business holdings and the estate of John S. Knight.
    - Correspondence, 1985 June 20-27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 783
  - Crowe, Timothy, 1990-2003; 1.5; 0.57 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box and 1 half box
    Timothy Crowe, Vice President and Chief Financial Officer 1990-1997. These six folders, dating 1990-1993, include papers regarding the financial issues related to the Foundation's move from Akron to Miami, employee benefits, and updates on the James L. Knight Estate's bequest to the Foundation. There are also portfolio updates, reports on Knight-Ridder share performance, investment strategies, a ten-year financial projection, and correspondence with the Finance Committee.
    - Correspondence, 1990 November 8-December 28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 784
      Correspondence from Tim Crowe regarding details of financial issues involved in the move of the Foundation from Akron to Miami, and new human resource information (medical and dental insurance coverage).
    - Compensation Information, 1991 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 1702
      Compensation Information, including present compensation chart, organization chart, job descriptions of professional staff, 1991 salary survey update from the Council on Foundations, TPF&C Correspondence. 2 copies.
    - Correspondence, 1991 January 22-December 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 785
      Correspondence from Tim Crowe regarding the Knight Commission on Intercollegiate Athletics Budget, an update on the John S. Knight Estate, the Foundation's KRI share portfolio, and the Foundation's general portfolio update.
    - Executive Compensation Study, 1991 August 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 1703
      Executive Compensation Study presentation to the Board of Trustees, 8/20/1991. Prepared by TPF&C.
    - Correspondence, 1992 January 7-December 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 786
      Correspondence from Tim Crowe regarding portfolio reports, new asset managers, a ten-year projection and financial history of the Foundation, memos to Finance Committee on investment strategies.
    - Correspondence, 1993 February 3-December 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 787
      Correspondence from Tim Crowe including memos to the Finance Committee on the status of investments and summaries of committee meetings and their highlights.
    - Correspondence re: Financial and Administrative Issues, 1994 April 13-1994 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 3763